A Finding Aid to the Morris Louis and Morris Louis Estate papers, circa 1910s-2007, bulk 1965-2000, in the Archives of American Art AAA.louimorr
Archives of American Art
Morris Louis and Morris Louis Estate papers
bulk 1965-2000
circa 1910s-2007
AAA.louimorr
Archives of American Art
17.8 Linear feet
The Morris Louis and Morris Louis Estate papers measure 17.8 linear feet and date from circa 1912-2007, with the bulk of the material dating from 1965-2000. The collection documents Morris Louis' career as a Color Field painter and founding participant in the Washington Color School, as well as the subsequent administration of his estate by his wife Marcella Brenner. Found within Morris Louis’ papers are biographical materials, correspondence, photographs, scattered financial records, notes, writings, printed materials, and a canvas sample. The Morris Louis Estate papers include records of gallery exhibitions, mostly André Emmerich Gallery; artwork inventories; legal records concerning the lawsuit Bernstein v. Brenner; financial records of the sale of Louis’ artwork; printed materials; writings about Louis; photographs of exhibition installations and artwork; and project files which include documentation of film projects by Robert Pierce Productions, a catalog raisonne, documentation of PBS documentaries, video recordings of the exhibition "Morris Louis Now", and numerous sound recordings of interviews with artists discussing Morris Louis conducted by Anita Faatz.
Louis, Morris, 1912-1962
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. Research Center. Many of the audio recordings and transcripts of interviews with 26 artists conducted by Anita Faatz in 1970-1971 are access restricted and written permission is required from the person interviewed. Please contact reference services for more information. Any use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 2 series.
Series 1: Morris Louis Papers, circa 1910s-1998 (2.9 linear feet; Boxes 1-3)
Series 2: Morris Louis Estate Papers, 1947-2007 (14.9 linear feet; Boxes 3-19, OV 20)
Biographical/Historical note
Morris Louis (1912-1962) was one of the earliest American Color Field painters, and, along with other Washington, D.C. painters, formed the movement known as the Washington Color School.
Born in Baltimore, M.D. to Russian immigrants Louis Bernstein and Cecelia Luckman, Morris Louis attended the Maryland Institute of Fine and Applied Arts from 1927-1932 and served as president of the Baltimore Artists' Association in 1935. During the Depression, he worked in New York City on the steering committee of the Easel Division of the Federal Arts Projects of the Works Project Administration (WPA). He exhibited Broken Bridge at the WPA Pavilion of the New York World's Fair in 1939.
In 1947, Louis married Marcella (Siegel) Brenner, and moved to Silver Spring, Maryland, a close suburb of Washington, D.C. where he taught private art classes and continued painting, using his apartment bedroom as a studio. In 1948, Louis participated in the Maryland Artists, 16th Annual Exhibition at the Baltimore Museum of Art, and began using Leonard Bocour's Magna acrylic paint, which he would use exclusively for the rest of his painting career.
In 1952, Morris Louis and Marcella Brenner moved to Washington, D.C. and set up a studio in his home where he would complete his most notable canvases. He began teaching at the Washington Workshop Center for the Arts and met artist Kenneth Noland who was also exploring Color Field painting. Through Noland, Louis met art critic Clement Greenberg in 1953, and they visited artist studios in New York City to study abstract expressionist works, including those by Helen Frankenthaler, Jackson Pollock, and Franz Kline. Louis and Noland were greatly influenced by Frankenthaler's staining technique, and Louis began experimenting with staining methods upon his return to Washington. Clement Greenberg became a life-long advocate for Louis and, in 1954, included Louis in the seminal group exhibition, "Emerging Talent," organized by Greenberg for the Kootz Gallery. In 1960, Andre Emmerich became his dealer in the United States and Lawrence Rubin represented him in Paris.
Using thinned Magna paint and unstretched, unprimed canvases, Louis created his works by rotating the canvas as the paint moved across and soaked in. Between 1958 and 1962 Louis produced three major series of paintings—the Veils, the Unfurleds, and the Stripes. Each series numbered more than one hundred canvases. Louis never documented his exact painting methods and would not allow anyone to watch him work, including his wife. His own worst critic, Louis destroyed many of his paintings that did meet his standards, including a large number of his earliest works and many created between 1954 and 1957. He also designated numerous surviving works for destruction prior to his death.
Louis was diagnosed with lung cancer on July 1, 1962 and died a few months later. The Andre Emmerich Gallery held a previously scheduled exhibition as planned, a month following Louis' death, as a memorial exhibition.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Morris Louis and Morris Louis Estate papers were donated by Marcella Brenner in several installments in 1976, 1986, and 1988. Subsequent donations in 2009 and 2012 were donated by Marcella Brenner via Ann M. Garfinkle, Executor. The Anita Faatz interviews were donated in 1976 by Marcella Brenner.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found at the Archives of American Art are the Marcella Brenner journals, 1962-2000. The Maryland Institute College of Art (MICA) also holds papers of Morris Louis and the Morris Louis Estate in their Morris Louis Study Collection.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the papers were microfilmed on reels 4988-4994. While the microfilm is available for interlibrary loan, researchers are advised that the microfilm is incomplete and does not reflect the order of the papers as described in this finding aid.
Scope and Contents note
The Morris Louis and Morris Louis Estate papers measure 17.8 linear feet and date from circa 1912-2007, with the bulk of the material dating from 1965-2000. The collection documents Morris Louis' career as a Color Field painter and founding participant in the Washington Color School, as well as the subsequent administration of his estate by his wife Marcella Brenner. Found within Morris Louis’ papers are biographical materials, correspondence, photographs, scattered financial records, notes, writings, printed materials, and a canvas sample. The Morris Louis Estate papers include records of gallery exhibitions, mostly André Emmerich Gallery; artwork inventories; legal records concerning the lawsuit Bernstein v. Brenner; financial records of the sale of Louis’ artwork; printed materials; writings about Louis; photographs of exhibition installations and artwork; and posthumous project files which include documentation of film projects by Robert Pierce Productions, a catalog raisonne, PBS documentaries, video recordings of the exhibition "Morris Louis Now", and numerous sound recordings of interviews with artists, many with transcripts, discussing Morris Louis and conducted by Anita Faatz.
Within the Morris Louis papers (circa 3 linear feet) are scattered biographical materials for Morris Louis and Marcella Brenner. Correspondence is with family friends, artists, and galleries, the bulk of which consists of photocopies. Of note are letters from Helen Frankenthaler, Clement Greenberg, Leonard Bocour, Kenneth Noland, and Anne Truitt. Business records include lists of artwork, receipts for art supplies, and scattered tax records. Six notebooks belonging to Morris Louis contain miscellaneous notes about students, studio rental payments, addresses, travel expenses, and a short list of paintings. There is one notebook of Marcella Brenner’s containing notes about expenses and addresses. Also found are printed materials, one canvas sample, and one embossing stamp. Photographs are of Morris Louis, Marcella Brenner, and the Bernstein family.
The majority of the collection (circa 15 linear feet) consists of records created and maintained by Marcella Brenner in the course of managing Louis’ estate and posthumous exhibitions and projects. There are numerous gallery exhibition records for many posthumous and retrospective exhibitions between 1965 through 2002, including those held at the Andre Emmerich Gallery, the Hirshhorn Museum, and numerous other U.S. and international galleries and museums. Louis' artwork is documented in highly detailed inventory lists and cards. Legal records document the lawsuit brought by the Bernstein family against Marcella Brenner which began in 1964 and ended in 1970 in favor of Brenner. Financial records document sales.
Printed materials include clippings, exhibition catalogs and announcements, and other miscellaneous materials. Writings include essays about Louis and manuscript copies of the book Trustee for the Human Race: Litigation over the Morris Louis Paintings written by Ruth S. Blau under contract for Marcella Brenner. Photographs are primarily of artwork depicted in exhibition installations. Project files are found for several posthumous documentary film projects and a catalog raisonne, and include a series of audio recordings of interviews of 27 artists conducted by Anita Faatz in 1970-1971. Artists interviewed include Clement Greenberg, Leonard Bocour, Andre Emmerich, Helen Frankenthaler, Kenneth Noland, and many others.
André Emmerich Gallery; Bocour, Leonard, 1910-; Brenner, Marcella, 1912-2007; Faatz, Anita J., (Anita Josephine); Frankenthaler, Helen, 1928-2011; Greenberg, Clement, 1909-1994; Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden.; Noland, Kenneth, 1924-2010; Robert Pierce/Films, Inc.; Truitt, Anne, 1921-; Abstract expressionism--New York (State)--New York; Art, Modern--20th century; Art--Study and teaching; Color-field painting; Interviews; Law and art--United States; Painters--United States; Photographs; Sound recordings; Transcripts; Video recordings; Washington Color School (Group of artists)
- Morris Louis Papers, bulk 1950-1962; circa 1910s-1998; Series 1; 2.9 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged as 7 subseries.
  1.1 Biographical Material, 1964-1966
  1.2 Correspondence, 1941-1998
  1.3 Business Records, 1948-1963
  1.4 Notebooks, circa 1947-1962
  1.5 Printed Material, 1937-1962
  1.6 Artifacts, circa 1950s
  1.7 Photographs, 1910s-1962
  Scope and Contents note
  Within the Morris Louis papers (circa 3 linear feet) are scattered biographical materials, including chronologies and resumes, for Morris Louis and Marcella Brenner. Correspondence is with family friends, artists, and galleries, the bulk of which consists of photocopies. Of note are letters from Helen Frankenthaler, Clement Greenberg, Leonard Bocour, Kenneth Noland, and Anne Truitt. Among the correspondence are condolence cards and guest book pages of a Louis exhibition at Andre Emmerich Gallery in 1961 with notable signatures. Business records include lists of artwork, receipts for art supplies, and scattered tax records.
  Six notebooks belonging to Morris Louis contain notes about house measurements, student attendance and payments, studio rental payments, addresses, travel expenses, and a short list of paintings with dimensions and numbers assigned by Louis. One notebook of Marcella Brenner’s contains notes about expenses, addresses, and miscellany. Printed materials include exhibition catalogs and announcements, brochures, and clippings. There is one canvas sample and one embossing stamp. Photographs are of Morris Louis, Marcella Brenner, and the Bernstein family.
  - Biographical Material, 1964-1966; 1.1
    Biographical materials include chronology drafts, resumes, a "'dialogue' with Dr. Ira Lewis" written by Louis, a handwritten recipe card, and a resume and biographical notes for Marcella Brenner.
    - Morris Louis Dialogue with Dr. Ira Lewis, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Morris Louis Recipe Card, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Biographical Accounts About Morris Louis, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Biographical Materials for Marcella Brenner, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, bulk 1957-1970; 1941-1998; 1.2
    Correspondence consists of letters to and from family, artists, and galleries. Many of the letters prior to 1962 are photocopies and thermofax copies of originals not included in the collection. Correspondence after 1962 is with galleries and artists (and others) primarily concerning artwork and exhibitions.
    Of note are letters from art critic Clement Greenberg and artists Helen Frankenthaler, Anne Truitt, Kenneth Noland, and others. Also included in correspondence are the guest book pages from a Morris Louis show at the Andre Emmerich Gallery in October 1961, with signatures of Clement Greenberg, Leonard Bocour, David Smith, Frank Stella, Paul Jenkins, Kenneth Noland, Philip Pearlstein, Alfred Leslie, Michael Fried, and others.
    - Bernstein Family, 1941-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, 1941-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6-26)
    - Condolence Cards to Marcella Brenner, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Personal Business Records, 1948-1963; 1.3
    Personal business records consist of lists of artwork, receipts for household and art supplies, and scattered banking and tax records.
    - Lists of Art Works, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Receipts, Automobile, 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 29-31)
    - Receipts, Bocour Paint, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 32-37)
    - Receipts, Chevy Chase Paint and Hardware Co., 1955-1962 (Box 1, Folder 38-43)
    - Receipts, Dyer Brothers, Inc., 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Receipts, Educational Institutions, 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Folders are arranged by type of expense (ex: household) and by vendor. Materials are arranged chronologically within the folders.
    - Receipts, Fezande and Sperrle, Inc., 1951-1960 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Receipts, George F. Muth Co., circa 1951 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Receipts, Headstone Purchase, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Receipts, Health Care, 1955-1962 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Receipts, Household Expenses, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 50-64)
    - Receipts, James McCutcheon & Co., circa 1952-circa 1953 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Receipts, John Boyle & Co., Inc., 1953-1962 (Box 1, Folder 66-72)
    - Receipts, John Boyle & Co., Inc., 1953-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Receipts, McIntire Hardware, circa 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Receipts, Miscellaneous, 1951-1960 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Receipts, Rohm & Haas Company, 1955-1961 (Box 2, Folder 6-14)
    - Receipts, Safeway, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Receipts, Shipment of Artwork, 1951-1960 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Receipts, Stockett-Fiske Co., 1951 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Receipts, Studio Rent, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Receipts, Travel Expenses, 1951-1962 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Receipts, Wick Byron-Brown, Inc., 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Banking Records, 1952-1962 (Box 2, Folder 21-51)
    - Income Tax Records, 1951-1962 (Box 2, Folder 52-55)
    - Personal Property Tax Returns, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Federal Tax Returns, Morris & Marcella, 1948-1961 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Notebooks, circa 1947-1962; 1.4
    There are six notebooks by Morris Louis and one belonging to Marcella Brenner. Notebook #1 contains various room measurements within an unnamed house with references to fixture costs. Notebooks #2-4 are daybooks containing records of payments and attendance of art students, studio rental payments, and some student addresses and phone numbers. Notebook #5 contains addresses as well as a short list of paintings with dimensions and numbers assigned by Louis. Notebook #6 includes New York travel expense lists and New York important addresses. Notebook #7 contains Marcella Brenner's notes about an education conference expenses and other miscellaneous notes and addresses.
    - Notebook 1, circa 1947-circa 1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Notebook 2, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Notebook 3, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Notebook 4, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Notebook 5 and Address Book, 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Notebook 6, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Notebook 7 (Marcella Brenner), 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material, 1937-1962; 1.5
    Printed material includes brochures, clippings, exhibition catalogs, and exhibition events and announcements.
    - Brochures, 1950-1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Clippings, 1950-1963 (Box 3, Folder 9-17)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Exhibition Catalogs: "Morris Louis, April 1959" (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Exhibition Catalogs: Galerie Lawrence, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Exhibition Catalogs: "Art Since 1950", 1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Exhibition Events & Announcements, 1937-1961 (Box 3, Folder 23-26)
  - Artifacts, circa 1950s; 1.6
    Artifacts include a canvas sample inscribed with "No. 26 Dawn," and an embossing stamp "for drawings" of Morris Louis.
    - Canvas Sample, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Embossing Stamp, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Photographs, 1910s-1962; 1.7
    Photographs include those of the Bernstein family, of Morris Louis, and of Morris Louis with Marcella Brenner. There are also metal printing plates of 4 Morris Louis photographs and copy prints, reproductions, and duplicates.
    - Bernstein Family Photographs, 1910s-1951 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Morris Louis Photographs, 1942-1960 (Box 3, Folder 30-32)
    - Morris Louis Photographs, Negatives, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Metal Plates of Morris Louis Photograph, circa 1956 (Box 3, Folder 34-35)
    - Morris Louis & Marcella Brenner Photographs, 1947-1962 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Morris Louis Photographs, Reproductions, circa 1943-1960 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Morris Louis Estate Papers, bulk 1965-2000; 1947-2007; Series 2; 14.9 Linear feet Boxes 3-19, OV 20
  The majority of the collection (circa 15 linear feet) consists of records created and maintained by Marcella Brenner in the course of managing Louis’ estate and posthumous exhibitions and projects. Gallery exhibition records include printed materials, photographs, slides, price lists, invoices, and scattered correspondence for many posthumous and retrospective exhibitions between 1965 through 2002. Files are found for several exhibitions at the Andre Emmerich Gallery, Baltimore Museum of Art, Boston Museum of Art, Corcoran Gallery of Art, Denver Art Museum, Hayward Gallery, Hirshhorn Museum, Jewish Museum, Museum of Modern Art, and numerous other U.S. and international galleries and museums.
  Louis' artwork is well-documented in highly detailed inventory lists and cards. Legal records document the lawsuit brought by the Bernstein family against Marcella Brenner which began in 1964 and ended in 1970 in favor of Brenner, as well as 25 years of correspondence between Brenner and attorney I. S. Weissbrodt. Extensive sales records are found in the financial records, as well as scattered tax records.
  Printed materials include calendars, clippings, exhibition catalogs and announcements, and other miscellaneous materials. Writings include essays about Louis and manuscript copies of the book Trustee for the Human Race: Litigation over the Morris Louis Paintings written by Ruth S. Blau under contract for Marcella Brenner. Photographs are primarily of artwork depicted in exhibition installations.
  Project files are found for several posthumous documentary film projects and a catalog raisonne. Several of the projects contain only interviews provided by Brenner in support of the project, but others contain original research documentation. One such project was a series of audio recordings of interviews commissioned by Brenner and conducted by Anita Faatz in 1970-1971 with 27 artists talking about Morris Louis, his work, their relationships with him, and his influences. Faatz conducted interviews with Clement Greenberg, Leonard Bocour, Andre Emmerich, Helen Frankenthaler, and Kenneth Noland, among many others.
  This series is arranged as 8 subseries.
  2.1 Gallery Exhibitions, 1947-2002
  2.2 Art Records and Inventories, 1960-1992
  2.3 Legal Records, 1962-1989
  2.4 Financial Records, 1959-1998
  2.5 Printed Material, 1960-2006
  2.6 Writings, 1963-1988
  2.7 Photographs, circa 1950s-2001
  2.8 Project Files, 1966-2007
  - Gallery Records, 1947-2002; 2.1
    Gallery records document numerous exhibitions and openings and include exhibition announcements, clippings, photographs, slides, price lists, invoices of artwork sales, notes of receipt and transfer of Morris Louis artwork, and communications with Marcella Brenner. Also included is one sound cassette of a Dore Ashton lecture on Morris Louis' Charred Journals exhibition at the Jewish Museum in 1997.
    The bulk of the gallery records document exhibitions held at the Andre Emmerich Gallery, which represented Morris Louis for over 50 years. Other galleries represented within the files include private collections, international museums, national museums, and permanent collections.
    - Andre Emmerich Gallery, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 38-43)
    - Andre Emmerich Gallery, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 1-14)
    - Andre Emmerich Gallery, 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 15-40)
    - Andre Emmerich Gallery, 1976-1979 (Box 4, Folder 41-56)
    - Andre Emmerich Gallery, 1980-1984 (Box 4, Folder 57-61)
    - Andre Emmerich Gallery, circa 1985-1995 (Box 5, Folder 1-14)
      Oversized material located in box 19, folder 1.
    - Andre Emmerich Gallery, Photographs, 1947-1962 (Box 5, Folder 15-18)
    - Ackland Art Museum, 1986-1990 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Auckland City Art Gallery, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Australian National Gallery, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Baltimore Museum of Art, 1977-1985 (Box 5, Folder 22-23)
    - Bezalel Academy of Art and Design, Morris Louis Gallery, 1979-1991 (Box 5, Folder 24-28)
      Oversized material located in box 19, folder 2.
    - Boston Museum of Fine Arts, 1975-1986 (Box 5, Folder 29-35)
    - Cleveland Museum, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Connor Contemporary Art, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - David Mirvish Gallery, 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Denver Art Museum, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Fort Worth Art Museum, 1973-1987 (Box 5, Folder 41-43)
    - Galerie Neufville, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Galerie Piltzer, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Greenville County Museum of Art, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Hayward Gallery, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 47-52)
    - Hayward Gallery, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Hirshhorn Museum & Sculpture Garden, 1974-1987 (Box 6, Folder 2-6)
    - Hirshhorn Museum & Sculpture Garden, Photographs, 1974-1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Hirshhorn Museum & Sculpture Garden, Slides, 1974-1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Hirshhorn Museum & Sculpture Garden, "Morris Louis" Film Screening, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Israel Museum, 1979-1991 (Box 6, Folder 10-16)
      Oversized material located in OV 20.
    - Jewish Museum, 1996-1997; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 6, Folder 17-18)
    - Louisiana Museum of Modern Art, 1974-1986 (Box 6, Folder 19-20)
    - Madrid U.S. Embassy Contemporary Art Collection, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Maryland Institute College of Art, Meyerhoff Gallery, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Musee de Grenoble, 1986-1998 (Box 6, Folder 23-27)
    - Museum of Modern Art, New York, 1973-1986 (Box 6, Folder 28-30)
    - Museum of Modern Art, Shiga, Japan, 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 31-34)
      Oversized material located in box 19, folder 3.